ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist delivering \$1.54B with 8+ years of proven experience. Established and scaled enterprise—level Digital Transformations across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Delivered core engineering AI solutions for British Petroleum and enabled Data Science's 69% AI market share within BP US Onshore Upstream O&G. Produced \$500M+ via a patent—pending computational chemistry solution for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Acquired 52% of Exploration & Development's AI/ML market and enabled the team's 69% AI/ML market share across the organization spearheading in-house AI development & Digital Transformation strategy.
- · Delivered 100% of the Q2/Q3 Agile Features in Data Science, Generative AI, and Machine Learning Engineering.
- · Architected key partnerships with the Subsurface Technology Team and the Head of Performance Optimization.
- · Orchestrated internal forums with Digital Transformation Leaders across Saudi Aramco, ADNOC, and the U.S. DOE.

Product Owner

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Realized \$4MM in annual cost reductions prioritizing developer resources to build and deploy ML Sand Flowback.
- · Coordinated stakeholder timelines and prioritized developer resources launching ML Drilling AFE Cost Prediction.
- · Productionalized Long-term Production Risk for Subsurface Technology Reservoir Engineering via Streamlit.
- · Coordinated between BP and the US Department of Energy on integrating technology for produced water optimization.
- · Oversaw the Azure to AWS cloud migration for the Salt Water Disposal and Productivity Index Power BI reports.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Generated \$977MM for Permian with a \$700MM NPV well development plan and \$277MM Drilling & Completions cost reductions by productionalizing Techlog AI Electrofacies enabling well prospecting and fluid mobility assessments.
- · Delivered \$540MM NPV for Permian Reservoir Engineering deploying AI Completions Optimization in Streamlit.
- · Drove \$20MM NPV for Eagle Ford Reservoir Engineering launching ML Refracturing Production Forecasting.
- · Collaborated with Subsurface Technology to address Eagle Ford wellbore instability projecting \$60MM cost savings.
- · Interfaced with the **Head of Performance Optimization** on engineered completions projecting a 10% 20% uplift.

Data Scientist

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed \$500M+ in forecasted annual cost reductions and provisioned Neural Processing Units to support patent—pending Automated Sensor Calibration advances directly on next—generation semiconductor sensor technologies.
- · Led a 21% enhancement in Mass Spec signal fidelity (SciPy.optimize/Statsmodels), designed A/B Quality Control tests (SciPy.stats/Nolds) for all Mass Spec sensors, and documented mathematical foundations for proprietary algorithms.
- · Established 50% coverage across chemical detection and monitoring systems designing KPIs and executing A/B simulation tests via synthetic GC–MS data generated using PySwarms and SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate.
- · Achieved a 95% increase in density estimation accuracy creating the Bijective Neural Architecture via PyTorch.

Technology Analyst

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

June 2016 – August 2016 Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and deployed code to live internal JPMC applications.

Software Engineer

Self-employed

June 2015 – September 2015 Syracuse, New York

· Engineered information retrieval systems as a subcontractor for **British Petroleum (BP)** and a **County Government**.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

August 2014 – May 2015 Syracuse, New York

Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

USPTO Application 18/686,753

August 2023 Patent Pending

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing

BP Geophysics R&D Seminar

Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity

INFICON Data Analytics Summit

November 2020

Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches

Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session

April 2018

July 2024

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

April 2024/December 2023

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

Havens Consulting

April 2023

Power BI — Reporting and Model Building

Havens Consulting

February 2023

HONORS & AWARDS

Graduate Merit Scholarship

Syracuse University

August 2017 – May 2018

Summa Cum Laude

Syracuse University

May 2017

May 2017

The Warren Semon Prize Syracuse University

Dean's Leadership Grant

Syracuse University

September 2014

Dean's List

Syracuse University

August 2014 – May 2017

The Founders' Scholarship August 2014 – May 2017

Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Syracuse University

May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University

May 2017

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Change Management, Agile, OKRs, CRISP-DM

Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling,

Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Monte Carlo, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining

Tools Amazon SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, R, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy,

NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog, Atlassian Jira, Azure DevOps